# **Abhishek Mittal**

amittal1311@gmail.com • +1 (514) 464-5855 • LinkedIn • GitHub • Portfolio

## **SUMMARY**

Bilingual **Software Engineer (English & French)**, bringing over 2 years of experience centered on **Backend Development**, **Frontend Design**, and **Cloud Technologies**. Detail & Result-Oriented and committed to deadlines & proactive approaches for reliability and scalability, currently seeking an opportunity to actively contribute towards company success.

## **EDUCATION**

CONCORDIA UNIVERSITY

Master of Science in Applied Computer Science

CHITKARA UNIVERSITY

Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Science

Montreal, QC 2021 - 2023 Himachal Pradesh, India 2016 - 2020

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

RUBIQ SOLUTIONS PVT. LTD.

Goa, India

## Software Development Engineer

SEPT 2019 - July 2021

- Led the design and development of microservices applications, generating \$1.3 million, using Java, Spring Boot, AWS, React, NodeJS, and Angular.
- Increased system efficiency by 30% by designing scalable APIs with Spring Boot, AWS Lambda, and other AWS technologies, serving
  thousands of daily requests.
- Optimized containerization and deployment with Docker and Kubernetes, reducing deployment time by 30% and improving scaling
  efficiency by 20%.
- Created and maintained database schemas, focusing on efficient modeling and using optimization techniques like indexing and sharding, reducing query response times by 30%.
- Applied Agile Methodologies including CI/CD, pull requests, code reviews, and testing (unit, load, stress and integration tests).

### KABERA GLOBAL TECHNOLOGIES PVT. LTD.

CHANDIGARH, India

### Software Engineer Intern

May 2019 - Aug 2019

- Optimized the system by resolving client defects and adding features through logic improvements and refactoring with lambdas and streams, reducing bug reports by 24% and increasing efficiency by 15%.
- Implemented a messaging architecture with Kafka, improving microservices communication by 20%.
- Developed a secure messaging feature using NodeJS and WebSocket, enabling real-time communication.
- Refactored unit tests with **JUnit** and **Mockito**, increasing code quality by 28%.
- Contributed to code reviews, reducing page load times by 15% and documented processes for efficient knowledge transfer.

## **PROJECTS**

## CAREER SERVICES PLATFORM | JAVA, SPRING BOOT, POSTGRESQL, REACT, NODEJS

• Led the development of a robust platform enabling employers to post job listings seamlessly, and candidates to browse and apply, capable of supporting 500+ simultaneous postings, accommodating 10,000+ active profiles, and handle 1000+ applications monthly.

### PLAGIARISM DETECTION PROGRAM | JAVA, DYNAMIC PROGRAMMING, ECLIPSE IDE

• Designed a Java-based plagiarism detection program for source code files and text documents, achieving a 94% success rate in identifying instances of plagiarism. The program supports files with sizes up to 25MB, ensuring comprehensive coverage and accuracy.

### HEALTHCARE SCHEDULING PLATFORM | JAVA, SPRING BOOT, REACT, NODEJS, MONGODB, POSTGRESQL

 Led the development of a comprehensive healthcare scheduling platform enabling users to seamlessly add and assign shifts, communicate with staffing coordinators, accept or cancel a shift request, review task lists and access payroll details, with a capacity to serve over 1,000 users.

### COLLEGE APPLICATION APPROVAL SYSTEM | JAVA, MYSQL, BOOTSTRAP

 Developed an application approval system for the university, streamlining administrative processes by 50%, enabling students to submit requests for admissions, leave, medical, and gate passes, while allowing teachers to review and respond to applications, access student profiles, and manage administrative changes efficiently. Voted "Project of the Year" by the university.

### FACE MASK DETECTION MODEL | CNN, TENSORFLOW, PYTHON

Led the development and deployment of a neural network model to detect different types of face masks, such as N95 and surgical
masks, on human faces. Collaborated on data cleaning and training tasks while applying bias detection techniques to ensure model
fairness. Achieved a detection accuracy of 75.68%.

## **SKILLS**

- Programming Languages: Java, JavaScript, C, C++, Python, SQL
- Technologies: Spring, AWS, React, NodeJS, Apache Kafka, MongoDB, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Kubernetes, Git, Jenkins, Figma
- Miscellaneous: Docker, Jira, JUnit, Mockito, Postman, Design Patterns, Agile/Waterfall Development, Microservices, Unit Testing, CI/CD, TDD, SDLC, REST, XML, JSON, MVC

## **CERTIFICATIONS**

Programming in C and C++ (CS Infotech), Full Stack Development (upGrad), Programming in Python (Udemy), Software Engineering Job Simulation (Hewlett Packard Enterprise, Forage), Advanced Software Engineering Job Simulation (Walmart Global Tech, Forage)

# Abhishek Mittal

amittal1311@gmail.com • +1 (514) 464-5855 • LinkedIn • GitHub • Portfolio

### RÉSUMÉ

Ingénieur Logiciel Bilingue (Anglais et Français), avec plus de 2 ans d'expérience axée sur le développement backend, la conception frontend, et les technologies cloud. Orienté sur les détails et les résultats, engagé à respecter les délais avec des approches proactives pour garantir fiabilité et évolutivité. Je suis actuellement à la recherche d'une opportunité pour contribuer activement au succès de l'entreprise.

### ÉDUCATION

CONCORDIA UNIVERSITY

Maîtrise en Sciences Appliquées en Informatique

CHITKARA UNIVERSITY

Baccalauréat en Ingénierie Informatique

Montréal, QC 2021 - 2023 Himachal Pradesh, Inde 2016 - 2020

### **EXPÉRIENCE PROFESSIONNELLE**

Rubiq Solutions Pvt. Ltd.

GOA, INDE

### Ingénieur Développement Logiciel

SEPTEMBRE 2019 - JUILLET 2021

- Dirigé la conception et le développement d'applications de microservices, générant 1.3 million \$, en utilisant Java, Spring Boot,
   AWS, React, NodeJS et Angular.
- Augmenté l'efficacité du système de 30 % en concevant des API évolutives avec Spring Boot, AWS Lambda, et d'autres technologies AWS, servant des milliers de requêtes quotidiennement.
- Optimisé la conteneurisation et le déploiement avec Docker et Kubernetes, réduisant le temps de déploiement de 30 % et améliorant l'efficacité de mise à l'échelle de 20 %.
- Créé et maintenu des schémas de base de données, en se concentrant sur une modélisation efficace et en utilisant des techniques d'optimisation comme les **index** et le **sharding**, réduisant le temps de réponse des requêtes de 30 %.
- Appliqué les pratiques Agile, incluant CI/CD, pull requests, revues de code, et tests (unitaires, de charge, de résistance, d'intégration).

KABERA GLOBAL TECHNOLOGIES PVT. LTD.

CHANDIGARH, INDE

### Stagiaire Ingénieur Logiciel

Mai 2019 - Août 2019

- Optimisé le système en résolvant les défauts clients et en ajoutant des fonctionnalités via des améliorations logiques et le refactorisation avec des lambdas et des streams, réduisant les rapports de bogues de 24 % et augmentant l'efficacité de 15 %.
- Implémenté une architecture de messagerie avec Kafka, améliorant la communication entre microservices de 20 %.
- Développé des fonctionnalités de messagerie sécurisée avec Node.js et WebSocket, permettant une communication en temps réel.
- Refactorisé les tests unitaires avec **JUnit** et **Mockito**, augmentant la qualité du code de 28 %.
- Contribué aux revues de code, réduisant le temps de chargement des pages de 15 % et documenté les processus pour un transfert de connaissances efficace.

#### **PROJETS**

### Plateforme de Services Carrière | Java, Spring Boot, PostgreSQL, React.js, Node.js

• Dirigé le développement d'une plateforme permettant aux employeurs de publier des offres d'emploi et aux candidats de postuler, capable de gérer plus de 500 annonces simultanées, 10000 profils actifs et 1000 candidatures par mois.

#### Programme de Détection de Plagiat | Java, Programmation Dynamique, Eclipse IDE

• Conçu un programme de détection de plagiat en **Java** pour les fichiers de code et les documents, atteignant un taux de succès de 94 % dans l'identification du plagiat. Le programme supporte des fichiers jusqu'à 25 Mo, garantissant précision et couverture complètes.

### Plateforme de Planification des soins de santé | Java, Spring Boot, React, NodeJS, MongoDB, PostgreSQL

• Dirigé le développement d'une plateforme complète de planification des soins de santé permettant aux utilisateurs d'ajouter et d'assigner des quarts de travail, de communiquer avec les coordinateurs de personnel, d'accepter ou d'annuler des demandes de quarts, de consulter des listes de tâches et d'accéder aux détails de la paie, avec une capacité de servir plus de 1000 utilisateurs.

### Système d'approbation des Demandes Universitaires | Java, MySQL, Bootstrap

• Développé un système d'approbation des demandes pour l'université, optimisant les processus administratifs de 50 %. Le système permet aux étudiants de soumettre des demandes d'admission, de congé, de certificat médical et de laissez-passer, tout en permettant aux enseignants de répondre aux demandes, d'accéder aux profils des étudiants et de gérer les changements administratifs efficacement. Élu Projet de l'Année par l'Université.

### Modèle de Détection de Masques Faciaux | CNN, TensorFlow, Python

 Dirigé le développement d'un modèle de réseau de neurones pour détecter différents types de masques faciaux, comme les N95 et chirurgicaux. Collaboré au nettoyage des données et à l'entraînement, en appliquant des techniques de détection de biais pour garantir l'équité du modèle, atteignant une précision de 75,68 %.

### **COMPÉTENCES**

- Langages de Programmation: Java, JavaScript, C, C++, Python, SQL
- Technologies: Spring, AWS, React, NodeJS, Apache Kafka, MongoDB, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Kubernetes, Git, Jenkins, Figma
- Divers: Docker, Jira, JUnit, Mockito, Postman, Modèles de Conception, Développement Agile/Waterfall, Microservices, Tests Unitaires, CI/CD, TDD, SDLC, REST, XML, JSON, MVC

## **CERTIFICATIONS**

Programmation en C et C++ (CS Infotech), Développement Full Stack (upGrad), Programmation en Python (Udemy), Simulation d'emploi en génie logiciel (Hewlett Packard Enterprise, Forage), Simulation d'emploi avancée en génie logiciel (Walmart Global Tech, Forage)